Guide to the Walter Brattain family papers 1860-1990
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
- Reference Materials, 1860-1989; 3; 6 linear feet
  - Trustees and Overseers, 1968-1976 (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Whitman College Alumni Association Appreciation Awards, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - "Whitman Scientists" – address by William Fairbank, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Why Whitman?, 1958-1979 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Amoy Club Rulebooks, 1898, 1902 (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - John Bardeen, 1968 (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - John Bardeen Biography, Encyclopedia Americana, 1965 (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - Brattain School article and photographs, undated (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - Harold Brown Inaugural Address, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - Bulletin of the College of Engineering National Chiao Tung University, 1971 – 1972 (Box 18, Folder 34)
  - Census of Lane County Oregon, 1860 (Box 18, Folder 35)
  - Colleagues' Addresses, undated (Box 18, Folder 36)
  - College Related Clippings (not Whitman), 1952-1964 (Box 18, Folder 37)
  - Electoral College, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 38)
  - "40 and 20 Years Ago in the Record", 1968 (Box 18, Folder 39)
  - Harvard, 1952, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 40)
  - High School Students, 1962 (Box 18, Folder 41)
  - "History of Inventions", undated (Box 18, Folder 42)
  - History of Physics Center, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - International Project in the History of Solid State Physics, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 44)
  - Invitation to Help Fund an International Council for Scientific Development, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 45)
  - James Killian Address, 1961 (Box 18, Folder 46)
  - Key Reporter, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 47)
  - Miscellaneous Articles, 1954-1980 (Box 18, Folder 48)
  - Naval Research Reviews, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 49)
  - "Night of the One-Eyed Devils", undated (Box 18, Folder 50)
  - China Tour and Presentation, 1979 (Box 18, Folder 51)
  - Recruiting, 1955 (Box 18, Folder 52)
  - The Science Fair Story of Electronics, 1983 (Box 18, Folder 53)
  - Scientific Source Materials: A Note on Their Preservation, 1963 (Box 18, Folder 54)
  - Scientists Obituaries, 1960-1981 (Box 18, Folder 55)
  - A Selection of Manuscript Collection at American Repositories, 1969 (Box 18, Folder 56)
  - Maria Stern Transcript, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 57)
  - "Time" Article on Invention, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 58)
  - University of Minnesota Clippings, 1957-1977 (Box 18, Folder 59)
  - University of Oregon, 1976 (Box 18, Folder 60)
  - Walla Walla Chamber of Commerce, 1956-1961 (Box 18, Folder 61)
  - The Widening Circle, 1958 (Box 18, Folder 62)
  - William Jewell College, 1977-1979 (Box 18, Folder 63)
  - The Transistor: Selected Reference Material on Characteristics and Applications, 1951 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - "Transistron = Transistor Plus?", 1950 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Education and Science Articles, 1974-1978 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Technology Review, 1981-1982 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Vacuum Tubes, 1915-1920 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Ling Wei Articles, 1972-1973 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Bell Telephone Laboratories, Electron Tubes and Varistors, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1964-1982 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - The White House, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Register of Ph.D. Degrees, University of Minnesota, 1888-1938, 1939 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - P.J. Boddy Articles, 1966, undated (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Physics Today Special Issue: John Bardeen, 1992 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - C.J. Davisson and L.H. Germer articles, 1922-1928 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Translated Articles, 1938-1964 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Neils Bohr Articles, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Materials Submitted to Franklin Mint Researcher, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Lillian Hartmann Hoddeson Essays, 1978-1980 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Reprinted Science Articles, 1921-1967 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Physics Today – 50 Years of Physics in America, 1981 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Moran School Pamphlets, 1914-1920 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Bell Laboratories Record, 1938, 1941, 1983 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Benjamin Brown – Oersted Medal, 1937-1950 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Benjamin Brown Fund, 1956 – 1977 (Box 19, Folder 23-24)
  - Bell Telephone System Technical Publications, 1925-1938 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Physics newsletters, 1967-1968 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Science: American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1976-1977 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Clippings from Scientific Magazines, 1967-1981 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Scientific Pamphlets, 1930-1976 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Adventures in Experimental Physics, vol. 5, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Electronics: Special Commemorative Issue, vol. 53, no. 9, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 10th International Conference on the Physics of Semiconductors, Extended Abstracts, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - C.L. Peterson, "Properties of Linear Active Four-Poles: Applications to Transistors", 1948 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - NBC Television Network, "The Story of Continental Classroom", undated (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Bell Telephone Laboratories, "Some Contributions to Transistor Electronics", 1949 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Congers Herring and M.H. Nichols, "Thermionic Emission", undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Cinquante Ans Avec Le Progres, copy specially printed for Walter Brattain, undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - "Lectures on Statistical Mechanics", undated (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Collected Stoic Papers, Volumes XVIII, XIX, AND XX, 1951-1961 (Box 20, Folder 15-17)
  - Scientific Publications, 1976-1983 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Bell Telephone System Monographs, 1946-1965 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Hunger in the World, Resolution Signed by Nobel Winners, 1981 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - "The Science Fair Story of Electronics," Radio Shack Educational Comic Book, 1982 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - "Transistors: Fundamentals for the Integrated-Circuit Engineer", 1983 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - "Progress in Electronics" envelopes and stamps, first day of issue, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Walla Walla League of Women Voters publications, 1962-1974 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Historical Clippings, undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Clippings about Walter Brattain, 1956-1987, undated (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Whitman College Alumni/Faculty Files on Walter Brattain, 1955-1987, undated (Box 21, Folder 9-11)
- Photographs, 1920-1981; 4; 1.7 linear feet
  Photographs document Walter Brattain's activities as a student, teacher, and scientist.
  - Glass Lantern Slides, 1956, undated; 1
    - Electronic Schematics, undated (Box 22, Folder 1-11)
    - Nobel Ceremony, 1956 (Box 22, Folder 12-22)
    - Graphs and Geological Illustrations, undated (Box 22, Folder 23-24)
  - Prints and Negatives, 1920-1981; 2
    - Portraits of Walter Brattain – small prints, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Portraits of Walter Brattain – large prints, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Portraits of Walter Brattain - negatives, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Four Horsemen of Physics: Walter Brattain, Walker Bleakney, Vladimir Rojansky, and E.J. Workman, 1924-1974, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - College Scenes, 1920-1976, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Whitman College, 1920-1978, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Teaching and Lectures, 1955-1973, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Laboratory Scenes, 1929-1979, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Time, Inc. Photographs of Walter Brattain, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Transistor Invention, undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Nobel Award Ceremony, 1956 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Awards and Celebrations, 1971-1981, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Conferences, 1950-1979, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Naval Research Advisory Committee, 1961-1967 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Gatherings and Colleagues, 1960-1981, undated (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Photographs and Posters of Walter Brattain and Collaborators at Bell Telephones, undated (Box 45, Folder 7)
- Audio and Video Recordings, 1960-1979, undated; 5; 1.8 linear feet
  Recordings include interviews and presentations about Walter Brattain, as well as other materials collected by him.
  - Vinyl Recordings – Oral Reminiscences of Nobel Ceremony, undated (Box 28)
  - 2 Tape Cassettes – Walker Bleakney Retirement Dinner, 1969 (Box 28)
  - Tape Cassette – Visit with Leonard Woodcock, 1979 (Box 28)
  - Tape Cassette – Escape From Russia (1917), A Personal Account by Vladimir Rojansky, February 1972 (Box 28)
  - Tape Cassette – George Castille Lecture, undated (Box 28)
  - Videocassette – "To Communicate is the Beginning", undated (Box 28)
  - 2 Videocassettes – Walter Brattain, Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), 1978 (Box 28)
  - Reel-to-Reel Tape: "Interview with the Inventors of the Transistor," transcript included, undated (Box 28)
  - 16 mm Film – National News: "Impact of Transistor – 25 Years!", undated (Box 28)
  - 16 mm Film – Science World: "Silver Anniversary for Transistors!", undated (Box 28)
  - Film Roll and Pamphlets – "Walter Brattain on Semiconductor Physics", undated (Box 29)
  - Unprocessed audiovisual records, circa 1960 - 1972; .5 linear feet 1 box (Box 47)
- Medals and Artifacts, 1924-1987; 6; 5.7 linear feet
  - Nobel Prize Personal Diploma, 1956 (Box 30)
  - Dictionary of International Biography Illustrated Plaque, 1979 (Box 30)
  - Wooden Plaque – Photographs of Walter Brattain, Walker Bleakney, E.J. Workman, and Vladimir B. Rojansky, 1924-1974 (Box 30)
  - Naval Weapons Center Advisory Board Plaque, 1967-1968 (Box 30)
  - Seattle World's Fair Bell Telephone Exhibit, 1962 (Box 30)
  - National Academy of Sciences Centennial Medal, 1963 (Box 30)
  - National Classical Music Institute Medallion, South Korea, 1973 (Box 30)
  - Seoul National University Wooden Medallion, undated (Box 30)
  - Seoul High School Visit Cloth Banner, 1973 (Box 30)
  - National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges Medal, 1987 (Box 30)
  - 50 Years of Electronics Commemorative Coin Plaque, 1980 (Box 30)
  - Columbia University World War II – For Participation in the Work of the Division of War Research (metal plaque), undated (Box 30)
  - Sigma Pi Sigma National Physics Honor Society Membership Certificate, William Jewell College, 1979 (Box 31)
  - Certificate of Life Membership in the Telephone Pioneers of America, undated (Box 31)
  - Sigma Pi Sigma Honorary Membership Plaque, 1979 (Box 31)
  - "Cernunnos," by Holly Sweeney (made out of semiconductor equipment and materials), 1977 (Box 32)
  - One of the First Radium Tubes for Inserting in Cancerous Tissue, undated (Box 33)
  - Pieces of Experiment Element (piece of "yellowcake" removed November 2008 and given to faculty member of Whitman College, undated (Box 33)
  - Transmitter, undated (Box 33)
  - John Scott Medal, 1954 (Box 46)
  - Nobel Prize Medal, 1956 (Box 46)
- Family Histories, 1911, undated; 7; 0.2 linear feet
  This series includes genealogical and historical information gathered about the Brattain and Houser families.
  - Brattain Family History, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Brattain Family Genealogy, undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - "Journal of the Oregon Trail" by Lafayette Spencer, mentions Paul Brattain, undated (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Agnes McCalley Brattain's Story, undated (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Frances Brattain Worthington's Story, undated (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Spokesman-Review article about Houser family flour mill at Colville, 1911 (Box 34, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1896-1987; 8; 1.8 linear feet
  Family correspondence has been sorted by family member, encompassing both incoming and outgoing letters. Some overlap exists with correspondence between family members, which has been filed under the sender's name when possible. Emma Jane, Keren, Ross and Ottilie, and Walter Brattain are major correspondents in this series.
  - From Agnes Brattain to Family, 1920-1942 (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - From Emma Jane to Walter Brattain, 1960-1961 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - From Emma Jane to Walter Brattain, 1962 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - From Emma Jane to Walter Brattain, 1963-1965 (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Cards and Letters to Emma Jane Brattain, 1962-1979 (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Cards and Letters to Emma Jane Brattain re: Walter Brattain's Death, 1987 (Box 34, Folder 12-13)
  - From Keren to Walter Brattain, 1934-1935 (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - From Keren Brattain to Family, 1935-1939 (Box 34, Folder 15)
  - From Keren Brattain to Family, 1940-1949 (Box 34, Folder 16)
  - From Keren Brattain to Family, 1950-1953 (Box 34, Folder 17)
  - To Keren Brattain from Family, 1921-1938 (Box 34, Folder 18)
  - Ottilie Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence (From China), 1896, 1901-1902 (Box 34, Folder 19)
  - Ottilie Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence, 1905-1910 (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - Ottilie Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence, 1913-1919 (Box 34, Folder 21)
  - Ottilie Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence, 1925, 1928-1929 (Box 34, Folder 22)
  - Ottilie Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence, 1942, 1954-1957 (Box 34, Folder 23)
  - Ross Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence (From China) (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Ross Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence, 1904-1921 (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Ross Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence (From China), 1924 (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Ross Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence, 1926-1947 (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Ross Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence (From Orogrande, Idaho), 1942-1956 (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Ross Brattain: Outgoing Correspondence (From Mercer Island), 1942-1960 (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: General Correspondence (In China), 1902 (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1901-1904 (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1907-1908 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1909-1910 (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1911-1915 (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1916-1927 (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Ross and Ottilie Brattain: Incoming Correspondence, 1928-1935, 1956 (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - From Walter Brattain to Family, 1915-1923 (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - From Walter Brattain to Family, 1926-1928 (Box 35, Folder 16)
  - From Walter Brattain to Family, 1929-1934 (Box 35, Folder 17)
  - From Walter Brattain to Family, 1935-1942 (Box 35, Folder 18)
  - From Walter to Keren Brattain, 1934-1935, 1939 (Box 35, Folder 19)
  - From Walter to Ottilie Brattain re: Transistor, 1948 (Box 35, Folder 20)
  - Walter Brattain Personal Correspondence, 1922-1957, undated (Box 35, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence re: Walter Brattain and Emma Jane Miller Wedding, 1958 (Box 35, Folder 22)
  - Letters from Brattain Relatives, 1903-1941 (Box 35, Folder 23)
- Family Personal Papers, 1897-1989; Series 9.; 0.8 linear feet
  Personal papers include writings and other documents generated or collected by Emma Jane, Ross, and other family members.
  - Emma Jane Brattain, 1946-1989; 1
    - Advertisements and Ephemera, 1946-1964, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Alaska Trip, 1976 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Booklets and Calendars, 1952-1984, undated (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Fifty-Year-Plus News Research Files, 1988-1989 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Rogers Walla Walla Canning Company/ Country Gardens Inc. Records, 1966-1967 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Roland Miller Papers, 1951-1954 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Walla Walla Symphony Society, 1973 - 1976 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Ross Brattain, 1901-1985; 2
    - Spokane High School Class Roll, undated (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Marriage Certificate of Ross and Ottilie Brattain, 1901 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Chinese Consul Appointment, 1902-1906 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Stock Certificates, 1905-1912 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Orogrande Mine Records, 1942-1957 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Writings and Reminiscences, 1958-1985, undated (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Family History Research, undated (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Wagon Wheel Blood, typed manuscript, undated (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Wagon Wheel Blood, excerpts and corrections, undated (Box 36, Folder 16)
    - Wagon Wheel Blood, corrected manuscript, 1979 (Box 36, Folder 17)
    - Wagon Wheel Blood, part one, undated (Box 36, Folder 18)
    - Wagon Wheel Blood, part two, undated (Box 36, Folder 19)
  - Other, 1897-1964; 3
    - Brattain Family Quit-Claim Deeds and Land Patents, 1916-1936 (Box 36, Folder 20)
    - Ottilie Houser, Whitman College report card, 1897 (Box 36, Folder 21)
    - Walter Brattain, Selective Service Notices of Classification, 1942-1943 (Box 36, Folder 22)
    - Planners and Notes, 1951-1964 (Box 36, Folder 23)
- Photographs, 1900-1904, 1950-1979, undated; 10; 2.6 linear feet
  Glass lantern slides document vivid scenes of daily life in China, including people, boats, temples, and landscapes. These slides were probably taken during Ross and Ottilie Brattain's time as missionaries there from 1901 to 1904. Prints and negatives include images of Brattain family members and travel scenes.
  - Glass Lantern Slides, circa 1901-1904; 1
    - 140 Glass Lantern Slides, circa 1901-1904 (Box 37, Folder 40)
  - Prints and Negatives, 1900-1904, 1950-1979, undated; 2
    - Portraits, undated (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Photo Album Pages, undated (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Travel and Leisure, 1950-1979, undated (Box 42)
    - Family History Research, 1900, undated (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - R. Robert Brattain Photographs, 1901-1902, undated (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Ross Brattain Photographs, undated (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - 11 Glass Plate Negatives – China, circa 1901-1904 (Box 44, Folder 4)
    - Sports Team Photographs, 1901 (Box 45, Folder 5)
- Artifacts and Clippings, 1901-1990; 11; 2 linear feet
  This series includes clippings about the Brattain family. A flour sack from the Tonasket Mill rounds out the series.
  - Tonasket Mill Flour Sack, undated (Box 45, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: The Brattain Family, 1901-1975 (Box 36, Folder 24)
  - Clippings: Walter Brattain's Death, 1987 (Box 36, Folder 25)
  - Emma Jane Brattain: Memorial Service and Obituary, 1990 (Box 36, Folder 26)